Roxbury, Boston, Mass. St. Mark's Social Center records, 1941-1966.
Congregational Library & Archives
Roxbury, Boston, Mass. St. Mark's Social Center records, 1941-1966.
RG0712
Congregational Library & Archives
1.03 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
The St. Mark's Social Center was founded in 1941 next to the St. Mark's Congregational Church in Roxbury, Massachusetts. The Social Center served as a meeting and community space primarily for the Black residents of Roxbury. After twenty-five years, the St. Mark's Social Center merged with the Ecumenical Center in 1967. This collection contains board of directors meeting minutes, treasurer records, records on the building of St. Mark's recreation center, spending reports, and financial records.
St. Mark's Social Center (Roxbury, Boston, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information is available for this collection.
Historical Note
The St. Mark's Social Center was founded in 1941 next to the St. Mark's Congregational Church in Roxbury, Massachusetts. During the Social Center's creation, the pastor of the church was Reverend Samuel Leroy Laviscount. Reverend Laviscount lead the Church for over thirty years and helped in it becoming a prominent congregation. From 1941 to 1966, both the Church and the Social Center were located on Townsend Street, where they were at the epicenter of life and learning in the local area.
The Social Center served as a meeting and community space primarily for the Black residents of Roxbury. There were many programs, events, and activities offered to youth especially, including use of St. Mark's nursery school, day camp, and recreation center and gymnasium. At the latter site, locals of all ages could swim, bowl, or play recreational sports. Whether they were children spending summers at the Social Center, teenagers attending seasonal dances, or adults participating in a variety of special interest groups, St. Mark's gave frequent opportunities for the community to come together.
During the Civil Rights Movement of the mid twentieth century, the Social Center made significant efforts to work with Boston residents. In 1964, the Social Center developed the first Freedom School in Boston under the leadership of the executive director at the time, Noel Day. Freedom Schools were created around the country to address the disparities and discrimination Black students faced in the American education system. The curriculum for Freedom School's such as the one affiliated with the St. Mark's Social Center focused on Black American history and sought to engage deeply with the students, thereby building their confidence and strengthening their voice.
On June 18, 1964, the St. Mark's Social Center served as the headquarters for a "stay-out" protesting segregation in the Boston Public School system. On this day, three thousand students, families, and friends did not attend class at the public schools of Boston but rather participated in workshops at Freedom Schools. The event was a pivotal moment in the Civil Rights Movement of Boston and aligned with the Social Center's overall practice of engaging in political, social, and cultural efforts of the surrounding area.
The running of the Social Center was not without some problems, as they faced a devastating fire in 1954 as well as occasional financial troubles. After twenty-five years of serving the people of Roxbury, the St. Mark's Social Center for Negro Boys & Girls merged with the Ecumenical Center in 1967, which was located at 25 Crawford St.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records on St. Mark's Social Center in Roxbury, Boston, Massachusetts and includes board of directors meeting minutes, treasurer records, records on the building of St. Mark's recreation center, spending reports, and financial records.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged by topic and then in chronological order.
Bibliography
Dwyer, Dialynn. "When Boston Students Called for Freedom." Boston.com, June 18, 2015. https://www.boston.com/news/history/2015/06/18/when-boston-students-called-for-freedom/.
Heath, Richard. "Washington Park Urban Renewal Program-Part I." Right Here in Roxbury Wiki. Accessed March 6, 2025. https://roxbury.fandom.com/wiki/Washington_Park_Urban_Renewal_Program-Part_I_by_Richard_Heath.
"Roxbury Timeline-1950-2005." Right Here in Roxbury Wiki. Accessed March 6, 2025. https://roxbury.fandom.com/wiki/Roxbury_Timeline-1950-2005
"Saint Mark's Congregational Church." Right Here in Roxbury Wiki. Accessed March 6, 2025. https://roxbury.fandom.com/wiki/Saint_Mark%27s_Congregational_Church.
Shelby Barthelemy. "St. Mark's Social Center." Clio: Your Guide to History. February 26, 2019. https://theclio.com/entry/75831.
"Wendolyn Love, 79, Was a Bookkeeper and Artist." The Vineyard Gazette, February 19, 2004. https://vineyardgazette.com/obituaries/2004/02/20/wendolyn-love-79-was-bookkeeper-and-artist.
Associations, institutions, etc.; African American Congregationalists.; Church finance.; Civil rights -- Religious aspects; Community Centers; Community development -- Religious aspects -- African American churches; Community development -- Roxbury (Boston, Mass); Day, Noel, 1933-; Laviscount, Samuel L., -1979; St. Mark's Congregational Church (Roxbury, Boston, Mass.); St. Mark's Social Center (Roxbury, Boston, Mass.)
- Recreation Building correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Recreation Building papers, 1941 1942; 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Recreation Building contract papers, 1941 1943; 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Monthly Financial reports, 1941 1966; 1941-1966; 1963 1966; 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Treasurer records, 1941 1948; 1941-1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Treasurer records, 1949 1954; 1949-1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Treasurer records, 1955 1959; 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Treasurer records, 1960 1964; 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Annual Financial reports, 1942 1966; 1942-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1944 1945; 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1946 1951; 1946-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1952 1954; 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1955 1957; 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1958 1960; 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1961 1963; 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Financial records, 1948 1953; 1948-1953 (Box 2, Volume 1)
- Financial records, 1953 1957; 1953-1957 (Box 2, Volume 2)
- Financial records, 1957 1961; 1957-1961 (Box 2, Volume 3)
- Monthly Spending reports, 1963 1965; 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)